[SPEAKER_00]: So, here are some questions.
[SPEAKER_00]: If I already recognize unwholesome intentions fairly quickly, how do I deepen my perception of their danger, so that I stop dismissing small acts as insignificant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, I think that just kind of boils down to how to practice the contemplation of danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: And, as I said before, you don't want to be just like a
[SPEAKER_01]: abstractly hammering in that everything is constantly dangerous all the time, or something, thinking you must, you must, like, reject everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's, it needs to be, it needs to be done only in regard to exactly these unwholesome intentions that you recognize, to the extent that they arise in terms of your habits, you know, ways of going about preferences.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through restraint, you don't give in, but then, when... even when things are acutely pressuring you to act out those intentions, that's when you have to be, like, broadening your horizon, so to speak, broadening the context, and contemplating new associations.
[SPEAKER_01]: Between the unwholesome intention and all the undesirable outcomes that are not necessarily immediately apparent, reminding yourself of it, of the results, of the lack of satisfaction and so on, whether you have the immediate kind of... those immediate intentions pressuring you or not,
[SPEAKER_01]: You need to be diligently making these associations.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, even if you're not acutely pressured by desire or to act out of ill-will,
[SPEAKER_01]: You still think about that when it does arise, I mustn't forget about the lack of satisfaction, the danger, the peril.
[SPEAKER_01]: And in terms of the danger and the peril, like, yeah, make associations between, like, liability to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not specific, like, oh, if I do this, this bad thing happens to me.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's more like, if I'm giving in to my mind now,
[SPEAKER_01]: on account of a desire that I know it's unbeneficial, but I don't quite see it as bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: Unwholesome, like sensual craving and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to recognize that it's the same mind state, then, that will arise when things, well, when things don't go my way, when things are outside of my control, when I'm being affected by circumstances or by other people and by so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: When the mind is being affected, it's going to act the same and I won't be able to calm it down.
[SPEAKER_01]: I won't be able to tell it, hey, hey, drop that.
[SPEAKER_01]: He won't, because I've been allowing him to take up things and not drop them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that is the also the connection between... that is the danger, like, because if you are not carelessly fueling desire and acting out of in unrestrained ways, like, then the mind would not be as as gripped or as resistant to unpleasant feelings and unfavorable experiences.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, he wouldn't suffer as much.
[SPEAKER_00]: It reminds me of, we spoke about it a while ago, that one might be, say, you know, lay people, say, drinking alcohol.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, I only drink, every now and then, I don't drink too much.
[SPEAKER_00]: But the fact is that you are creating a habit.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, why do you drink?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, drink, you know, to have fun, to relax and so on, because you are stressed somehow.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that stress, because of the stress, you go to drinking to relax.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, what if the stress increases twentyfold?
[SPEAKER_00]: It's the default.
[SPEAKER_00]: Is that in your control?
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, you've built up this habit of dealing with stress by giving in to alcohol in particular.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even if it's not the stress, even if it's just like habit, social pressure.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, people can do it for all sorts of reasons.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yes, moderation is better than excess.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're still moderating the same unwholesome roots, means they are still continuing to be alive.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like those roots, those habits.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when circumstances change, your reasons might change, just environment might change,
[SPEAKER_01]: And also, moderation is relative as well.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, what's moderate for somebody, it's not moderate for somebody else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, either way, you're maintaining the same habit that is keeping the mind, like, not under your control, is maintaining the... keeping the thread alive of that mental wilderness, because it can get out of hand.
[SPEAKER_01]: And certainly, even if it doesn't get out of hand in terms of the alcohol precept, it can get out of hand in other precepts, when the mind gets pressured by, or stressed, or influenced by other things of the unwholesome nature, because you haven't really set up the clear boundaries for it beforehand, it will spill out, it will run out, it will cause damage, it will try and attack you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or harm you, basically cause you to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's the principle behind.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yeah, I only have one drink out with friends to not stand out or something like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yes, that's factually hundredfold better than, you know, binge drinking.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, the principle behind is giving in to little ways to appease the wilderness of the mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: and not being able to draw a firm line, especially in regard to things that are completely unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, you could say, well, I need to eat, I need to do this, and it's kind of... it can be infected with desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, yeah, that's... it's going to take more time, and it's a... it's a subtler thing to separate, you know, eating without a desire for the purpose of just maintaining the body, or eating with the desire for the purpose of enjoying sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: But things like alcohol, sensual misconduct, drug and stuff, like, they're completely unnecessary.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if you have a choice, like, oh, here you are, trying to contain your mind, make yourself stronger in regard to the mind, make the mind stronger, and yet, a mere, measly, peer pressure of have a drink to not stand out, you have to give in, because you can't bear that awkwardness.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, so you can't expect mental strength to come out of that behavior.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, yeah, it's not as bad, but it's certainly not good enough either.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why, like, things that are unnecessary, the principle has to be protected.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if you can manage, even if the alcohol doesn't affect you as much, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: The fact is, why are you giving in in the first place?
[SPEAKER_01]: If it's not important, why do it anyway?
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's a kind of like that, similar in the Sutta, where the Buddha would...
[SPEAKER_01]: He didn't make a rule, but he suggested to the monks, like, oh, maybe just eat in one go.
[SPEAKER_01]: Don't eat multiple times.
[SPEAKER_01]: It would be better for your health, better for the mind, but he didn't make a specific rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it was like some of the monks were like, well, that's insignificant, really.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not important.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, I'll continue eating many times and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then other monks said, oh, well, that's insignificant, that's unimportant, and therefore they stopped.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he said the ones they stopped are like the the big elephant being, powerful elephant being strapped down by the leather straps.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're gonna keep him down, but he can break them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So he breaks the straps and frees himself from it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's like, like taking on that additional insignificant sense restraint will feel like massive leather straps now.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, because you took it on, the mind can grow out of it and break free.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then it says, but those that don't take it on, they are like, yes, it is factually insignificant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's, it is like, like a rotten ropes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Worn down ropes.
[SPEAKER_01]: But because you don't take it on, you're like a quail in regard to those ropes.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which means, even the rotten ropes, which are objectively weak, you will be weaker than them.
[SPEAKER_01]: So the quail will not be able to escape.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's kind of that little point.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you recognize something as factually insignificant, even if it's not outright unwholesome,
[SPEAKER_01]: You know, it's bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like having a drink for the social function.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not like immoral or bad.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it is unnecessary, and it goes against the principle that kind of threatens the whole mental development.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, when you recognize that, and the point will be what everybody who tries to practice will recognize things like that.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, oh, this is factually insignificant, but it still kind of carries a bit of a desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, what do you do then?
[SPEAKER_01]: Do then say, oh, it's insignificant, therefore,
[SPEAKER_01]: Carrying a bit of desire is also insignificant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or do you say, oh, it's insignificant, factually, objectively.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it does carry a desire for me, in this instance, out of my preferences, my habit, whatever, my color, doesn't matter for why.
[SPEAKER_01]: For whatever reason, there is desire involved.
[SPEAKER_01]: Therefore, I shouldn't do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's when you see the difference between, like, if you decide to not do it, it just feels insignificant, but the mind remains weak.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you decide to say no to it, oh, it suddenly ceases to be so insignificant, because the mind will resist against it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will become like a wild elephant.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, oh, but the leather straps... That's how it's going to feel, like you've been pulled by the leather straps.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, because you did say no, you actually
[SPEAKER_01]: Directed, say, you're training that way, and those habits, those little desire-dependent things now, the desire will be... will evaporate gradually out of it, and then it will be like a leather straps that kept the elephant down, then you restrain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, because the elephant became stronger in regard to the newly imposed threshold of what needs to be freed from, it will break free.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will break free.
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you didn't impose that threshold,
[SPEAKER_01]: It would have remained objectively insignificant, yet you would have remained bound by it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what I mean.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't go and have to say no to everything and, oh, this is insignificant, this is like...
[SPEAKER_01]: It has to be informed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Informed by the actual state of mind in regard to it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's easy to give up things that you don't care about.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it's like, okay, but let me find these things that are...
[SPEAKER_01]: Objectively neutral, or close to neutral.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, that for whatever reason, I do kind of depend on doing, relish doing, like doing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And let me just almost like experimentally say no to them for a while.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just to see, will my mind resist to this?
[SPEAKER_01]: And to what extent?
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if the mind resists, even if it's objectively insignificant, means it's not objectively insignificant for you.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's how you're learning also, in the same way, to start using your currently enduring states of mind as an actual guiding principle.
[SPEAKER_01]: As a reference point, not just this must be done, and that must be done, and mindlessly I'll just abandon, say no to these things, and cultivate these things.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's... All that's kind of in the abstract ether, divorced from the actual living practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, you have to start that way when you learn about it, but the point is, you need to know that the core kind of reference point that should be providing
[SPEAKER_01]: Your decisions as to, like, I'll give this up and it's the state of mind in regard to those things.
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it affected with desire?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it affected with ill-will?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it affected with impatience?
[SPEAKER_01]: Is it affected with all these?
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, okay, so that's what tells me what needs to be developed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not just like a blind sense of duty, because the Ajahn said these are the things and therefore I'll just...
[SPEAKER_01]: It might not have the same effect on you, because your mind might not be reacting or having the same sort of preferences, positive or negative, towards those things in the same way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, obviously, you know, the precepts are the groundwork.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's the basis.
[SPEAKER_01]: Everybody will be contained by the precepts.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because they pertain to the obvious, you know, central outpours, ill-will and distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: But we're talking about now, for like, say, you are keeping the precepts, but now within that, you are recognizing certain things that still kind of maintain these unskillful habits of your mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: So it's like, oh, so how do I now get to work with that?
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a requirement.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even that rule about the Buddha didn't make it a rule.
[SPEAKER_01]: Didn't just...
[SPEAKER_01]: He encouraged monks, and then, yes, some followed, some didn't.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he explained why those who didn't remained weak, and why those who followed what he said actually grew stronger.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that doesn't mean, like, you just will grow stronger magically by saying no to more things you say no, the stronger you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: No, it needs to be actually rooted in that which mind wants, resists, and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then say no to the right level, to the right thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: And for that, you need to be seeing the mind, seeing the preferences, seeing their influence over your actions, and not like justifying them, avoiding them, letting them spill out too much, but actually getting closer and closer to taking them on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, no, mind wants this, but I'm the one who decides that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Day or night, it doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: It doesn't matter.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I'm always in a position to to guide my mind, not other way around.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't let myself being guided by the mind under influence.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it's like seeing those...
[SPEAKER_00]: Any small act that is unwholesome, any small intention, evil intention that's unwholesome, even if it's just small, it still carries with it the liability to proliferate and suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: But also recognizing at the same time that simply saying no to the small intention will not automatically free your mind from from the issues.
[SPEAKER_01]: From the influence, from the desires and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like recognizing that saying no is just so that you get closer to that mental preference and can see it in the full extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it might not be that small at all.
[SPEAKER_01]: And something that was so big and frightful, you do the same and it turns out it might not be that big and frightful.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, your mind will tell you how much you wanted it, when you put a limit on it.
[SPEAKER_01]: When you refrain from doing it, when you refrain from following it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But again, you're not doing it blindly to just like, I'll just say no to everything.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're doing it just to see the extent that the mind comes up with.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then it's like, oh, well, look.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, that has to be endured, because that is the state of an animal when it didn't get what it wants.
[SPEAKER_01]: Even if it was objectively insignificant, it wasn't objectively insignificant for it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because if it were, it wouldn't have minded.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want, basically, to teach the animal, teach your citta, to be able to calm down after not getting what it wanted, through your own decision.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you wanted something,
[SPEAKER_01]: And it was not necessary for life, necessary for survival, necessary for whatever.
[SPEAKER_01]: It was unnecessary, rooted in unwholesome, partaking in desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you say no, just to reveal the extent of the citta, and then stay with it, until it eventually tires itself from trying to get out of the confinement, and calms down.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you recognize, oh, okay, I can calm down even without getting what I want, even without having to go through the motion of attaining what I need, what my desires require, fighting for it, protecting it, because that was the only form of peace that the wild animal knew, was satisfying what I need.
[SPEAKER_01]: It never put two and two together.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why...
[SPEAKER_01]: But, again, there is a difference between whether restraint is imposed by you, due to the place you live, requirements, authority, or whether it actually comes from your choice, that has no other reason to keep up.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like, oh, I have to do...
[SPEAKER_01]: I must not do this, because people will put me in jail.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like the outside criteria, outside authority kind of takes away responsibility or a degree of responsibility for restraint.
[SPEAKER_01]: I do it because I'll be...
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't do it because I'll be punished.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like that can help maybe for somebody initially, but it needs to come from you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I do it for no other reason except for me choosing to not do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: To teach the mind a lesson and take it away from dependence on sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: And there is no external reason, there is no external justification, there is no external authority of the world because of which you do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So then it feels truly you have no reason to do it, so to speak, yet you choose to do it.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's what you want to work to.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you need external support in that sense, the authority, the priesthood, the fear of shame, wrongdoing, as the Sutta says.
[SPEAKER_01]: But it needs to come to the point of, I don't do it for any other external reason, except for me wanting to directly teach the animal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's me choosing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And everything else tells me that I should stop, and I shouldn't do it, and there is no reason to do it, and it's an insignificant thing, and I don't really have to sustain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yet, I choose to do it because of all these things are trying to make me stop doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's you that's suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's you.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: The ultimate result of that training is it will be beneficial for both you and the animal, so to speak.
[SPEAKER_01]: For the experience as a whole will be cleansed of suffering and possibility to suffer.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yes, that is the ultimate goal, but it's kind of... can become abstract and far removed in the times when the mind is acutely pressured by desire, or to act out of ill-will, or to get what it wants, or to avoid, to run away from what it doesn't want.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's like, as I said, and even the whole world says, oh, yeah, you can, of course, you can do it, it's fine.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, no, but I'm not doing it, because I see that that directly taps back into the wilderness of an untrained mind, and it supports it further and continues it.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's like, I won't do it for that reason, because that is the ultimate danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: Untrained mind is the ultimate danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's really the only danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: And the only thing that needs to be done... And the only thing that needs to be fixed.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't need to fix the world, or circumstances, or elements, and aggregates.
[SPEAKER_01]: You just need to fix, basically, the untamed mind.